A Guide to the Virginia Magna Carta Commission of 1965, Records, 1963-1966
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1963-1966
Library of Virginia
26516
1.45 cubic feet
Virginia Magna Carta Commission of 1965
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Commission on Constitutional Government, June 28, 1966.
Historical Information
The Magna Carta Commission was established by an act of the General Assembly passed on March 31, 1964. The Commission consisted of fifteen appointed members. Three members were members of the Senate, appointed by the President of the Senate; four members were members of the House of Delegates, appointed by the Speaker of the House; and eight members were appointed by the Governor, one of whom, James Jackson Kilpatrick, served as Chairman. The at-large members were broadly representative of the public. The members received no salaries but were reimbursed for actual expenses incurred.
The Commission was authorized and directed to plan and present a suitable program commemorating the 750th anniversary of the signing of the Magna Carta on June 15, 1215. A.S. Harrison, Jr., Governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia, proclaimed Tuesday, June 15, 1965, Magna Carta Day. The Commission was authorized to solicit and receive gifts and contributions to be used toward the program; to cooperate with public and private groups and organizations in promoting, advertising, and stimulating interest in the program; and to perform all other acts necessary or incidental to performing the duties. All funds received were deposited in the State Treasury. The sum of twenty thousand dollars was appropriated. The Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government provided secretarial and clerical services for the Commission. The Commission ceased operations on July 31, 1965.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the administrative records of the Magna Carta Commission of Virginia, documenting the celebration of the 750th anniversary of the signing of the Magna Carta in 1965. Included in the collection are correspondence, research materials, publications, and photograph documenting the preparation and celebration of this occassion. The collection is organized into four series.
Series I. Administrative Records. This series contains the administrative papers of the Magna Carta Commission, including information regarding the Commission's establishment and dissolution, meeting minutes, and other administrative functions.
Series II. Magna Carta. This series contains background information about and texts of the Magna Carta.
Series III. Magna Carta Day, June 15, 1965. This series contains documentation regarding the observance of Magna Carta Day, including correspondence with participants and others, press releases, and correspondence with the United States Post Office Department regarding the Magna Carta Stamp.
Series IV. Publications. This series contains correspondence, publication drafts and other materials relating to the publications issued by the Magna Carta Commission. Please note that all of the original folder titles were retained as they were maintained by the Magna Carta Commission.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Organization
The collection is organized into four (4) series: I. Administrative Records; II. Magna Carta; III. Magna Carta Day, June 15, 1965; and IV. Publications.
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1963-1966
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Correspondence regarding the establishment and dissolution, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Financial Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notices of Meetings, Correspondence from Members, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Organization: Act, Members, Bylaws (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stationary (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Magna Carta
  - English Background and Events (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Texts of Magna Carta (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speeches about the Magna Carta (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Magna Carta Day, June 15, 1965, 1963-1965
  - Address of The Lord Chief Justice of England, 1965 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - After Magna Carta Day, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with other groups, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitations, Magna Carta Day, June 15, 1965, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lord Parker, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Magna Carta Day (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Magna Carta Day Arrangements, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Magna Carta Day Program Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - News Releases, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Post Office Dept., Magna Carta Stamp, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Promotion, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Reservations, Magna Carta Day, 1965 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with David De Boinville, British Embassy, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Recognition of anniversary in other places (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Publications
  - Publications Committee, 1964-1966, fo. 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Publications Committee, 1964-1966, fo. 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Publications Committee, 1964-1966, fo. 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Publications Distribution (free), orders and lists, 1964-1966, fo. 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Publications Distribution (free), orders and lists, 1964-1966, fo. 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Publications Sales and Collections, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Essays published by the Magna Carta Commission (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Publications Committee, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)